<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alexdong.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alexdong.com//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-29T09:26:32+12:00</updated><id>https://alexdong.com//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stream of thoughts from Alex Dong</title><subtitle>What I find interesting, intriguing or insightful.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A broader view on blue/red team</title><link href="https://alexdong.com//2025/07/29/a-broader-view-on-blue-red-team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A broader view on blue/red team" /><published>2025-07-29T09:17:00+12:00</published><updated>2025-07-29T09:17:00+12:00</updated><id>https://alexdong.com//2025/07/29/a-broader-view-on-blue-red-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexdong.com//2025/07/29/a-broader-view-on-blue-red-team.html"><![CDATA[<p>Terence Tao wrote about blue and red teams in the context of working with AI.
https://mathstodon.xyz/@tao</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the field of cybersecurity, a distinction is made between the “blue team”
task of building a secure system, and the “red team” task of locating
vulnerabilities in such systems.  The blue team is more obviously necessary
to create the desired product; but the red team is just as essential, given
the damage that can result from deploying insecure systems.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Blue teams are builders who create orders from chaos, while red teams are
invaders who finds inconsistencies, the weakest link, in a coherent whole and
punch holes in it.</p>

<p>An unexpected insight is red teams compound faster.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The nature of these teams mirror each other; mathematicians would call them
“dual”.  The output of a blue team is only as strong as its weakest link: a
security system that consists of a strong component and a weak component
(e.g., a house with a securely locked door, but an open window) will be
insecure (and in fact worse, because the strong component may convey a false
sense of security).  Dually, the contributions to a red team can often be
additive: a red team report that contains both a serious vulnerability and a
more trivial one is more useful than a report that only contains the serious
issue, as it is valuable to have the blue team address both vulnerabilities.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From organisational design perspective, slightly weird/unconventional
contributors are more suitable for playing the red team role.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Terence Tao wrote about blue and red teams in the context of working with AI. https://mathstodon.xyz/@tao]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This is to have succeeded.</title><link href="https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/Emerson-quote-this-is-to-have-succeeded.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This is to have succeeded." /><published>2022-10-31T14:38:00+13:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T14:38:00+13:00</updated><id>https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/Emerson-quote-this-is-to-have-succeeded</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/Emerson-quote-this-is-to-have-succeeded.html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I printed out a quote from Emerson and put onto our fridge 
so we can all look at it everyday.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To laugh often and much; to win the respect of intelligent people and
the affection of children; to earn the appreciation of honest critics
and endure the betrayal of false friends; to appreciate beauty; to
find the best in others; to leave the world a bit better, whether by a
healthy child, a garden patch, or a redeemed social condition; to know
even one life has breathed easier because you have lived. This is to
have succeeded.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today, I printed out a quote from Emerson and put onto our fridge so we can all look at it everyday.]]></summary></entry></feed>