<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alexdong.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alexdong.com//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-31T21:25:31+13:00</updated><id>https://alexdong.com//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Letters to Mia</title><subtitle>One day, you&apos;ll understand.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Let me speak through these text</title><link href="https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/what-made-me-want-to-write-this-blog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let me speak through these text" /><published>2022-10-31T21:19:00+13:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T21:19:00+13:00</updated><id>https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/what-made-me-want-to-write-this-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/what-made-me-want-to-write-this-blog.html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey Mia,</p>

<p>Here is why I decided to write this blog.</p>

<p>I was listening to <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/nz/podcast/people-i-mostly-admire/id1525936566?i=1000551594029">The only COVID-19 book worth
reading</a>.
The conversation was mainly about Michael Lewis’s book on COVID-19 and CDC.  But
towards the end, Michael shared the story of losing his daughter to a car
accident.</p>

<p>Standing there by the strawberry patch, I remain motionless for a few minutes. 
Overwhelmed by the sadness for Michael.</p>

<p>Life is unpredictable. Life is short. life is fragile. And we can’t do anything
about it.</p>

<p>By the time you reach 45, which is how old I am when I am writing this sentence,
I would be 82 years old. And there is a 50-50 chance that I won’t be here for you.
(NZ’s <a href="https://www.stats.govt.nz/news/growth-in-life-expectancy-slows/">male average life expectency is 82</a>.)</p>

<p>It scares me to realise that I won’t be here with you. The possibility has
always been here but I have never really thought about it until hearing about
Michael’s story.</p>

<p>So at that moment, I promised myself that I will start writing down what is
happening in our life; what has been going through in my mind everyday, and what
challenges I’m facing and how I dealt with it.</p>

<p>I hope that one day in the future, when you wake up and say to yourself “I
really wish I can talk to daddy now”, you can find me speaking to you thorugh
these writings.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hey Mia,]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This is to have succeeded.</title><link href="https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/Emerson-quote-this-is-to-have-succeeded.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This is to have succeeded." /><published>2022-10-31T14:38:00+13:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T14:38:00+13:00</updated><id>https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/Emerson-quote-this-is-to-have-succeeded</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexdong.com//life/2022/10/31/Emerson-quote-this-is-to-have-succeeded.html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I printed out a quote from Emerson and put onto our fridge 
so we can all look at it everyday.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To laugh often and much; to win the respect of intelligent people and
the affection of children; to earn the appreciation of honest critics
and endure the betrayal of false friends; to appreciate beauty; to
find the best in others; to leave the world a bit better, whether by a
healthy child, a garden patch, or a redeemed social condition; to know
even one life has breathed easier because you have lived. This is to
have succeeded.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today, I printed out a quote from Emerson and put onto our fridge so we can all look at it everyday.]]></summary></entry></feed>